Register of the Norman C. Stines Papers, 1911-1968
Hoover Institution Archives
Norman C. Stines Papers,
1911-1968
81097
Stines, Norman Caswell, 1914-1980
4 manuscript boxes, 14 envelopes 3.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Letters, printed matter, and photographs, relating to social conditions in Bolivia, Guatemala, Yugoslavia, and the Soviet Union, and to United States Department of State loyalty investigations. Includes letters of the parents of N. C. Stines, Americans in Russia during the Russian Revolution
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
United States. Dept. of State; Internal security--United States; Bolivia; Bolivia--Social conditions; Guatemala; Guatemala--Social conditions; Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Soviet Union--Social conditions; United States--Foreign relations; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union; Yugoslavia; Yugoslavia--Social conditions; Diplomats--United States
Biographical Note
Norman Caswell Stines
1914, August 6 Born, Stockholm, Sweden
1935 A.B., Stanford University
1936-38 Journalist, Redwood City Tribune
1938-39 Purchasing Agent for mining corporation in La Paz, Bolivia
1939-1942 Assistant Manager of electric company in La Paz, Bolivia
1942 Junior Economic Analyst in Foreign Service Auxiliary, La Paz, Bolivia
1943 Senior Economic Analyst in Foreign Service Auxiliary, La Paz, Bolivia
1944 Attache at the U.S. Embassy in Guatemala
1945-46 Vice Consul, Foreign Service Office, and secretary at the U.S. Embassy in Guatemala
1947-49 2nd Secretary and Vice Consul at the U.S. Embassy, Belgrade, Yugoslavia
1949 Foreign Service training at Columbia University, Russian language and area study
1950 2nd Secretary and Consul at the U.S. Embassy, Moscow USSR
1950-52 1st Secretary and Consul at the U.S. Embassy, Moscow, USSR
1953 Left the U.S. State Department service because of security investigations
1980 Died, Cuernavaca, Mexico
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1917-1968. (Box Box No. 1)
  Identification cards, certificates, clippings, government records, and printed matter pertaining to the life and career of N.C. Stines, Jr.
- Correspondence, 1911-1959. (Box Box No. 1-4)
  Correspondence arranged chronologically and alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Speeches and Writings, 1941, 1963. (Box Box No. 4)
  One radio broadcast transcript and one unpublished article filed by title.
- Subject File. (Box Box No. 4)
  Notes and printed matter arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Photographs (Box 81097 - 10.A-V)
Container List
- Biographical File, 1917-1968
  - Announcements, brochures, printed matter (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Clippings (Folder 2)
  - Department of State records, 1947-1952 (Folder 3)
  - Identification cards, certificates, etc. (Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1911-1959
  - Carroll, Vi M., 1947-1951 (Box 1., Folder 5)
  - Hopkins, Frank S., 1950 (Folder 6)
  - McConaughy, Walter P., n.d. (Folder 7)
  - Marie, 1939 (Folder 8)
  - Oliver and Ann, 1941 (Folder 9)
  - Preble, C. S., 1939 (Folder 10)
  - Reynaldo, 1941 (Folder 11)
  - Smith, Robert T., 1938, 1952 (Folder 12)
  - Stines, Hazel Preble
    - Letter to Norman C. Stines, Jr., 1936 (Folder 13)
    - Letters from Norman C. Stines, Jr.
      - 1936 (Folder 14)
      - 1938
        - January-March (Folder 15)
        - April-December (Folder 16)
      - 1939
        - January-July (Folder 17)
        - August-December (Folder 18)
      - 1940
        - January-July (Box 2., Folder 1)
        - August-December (Folder 2)
      - 1941
        - January-August (Folder 3)
        - September-December (Folder 4)
      - 1942 (Folder 5)
      - 1943-44 (Folder 6)
      - 1945 (Folder 7)
      - 1946 (Folder 8)
      - 1947 (Folder 9)
      - 1948-49 (Folder 10)
      - 1950 (Box 3., Folder 1)
      - 1951 (Folder 2)
      - 1952 (Folder 3)
      - 1955 (Folder 4)
      - 1959 (Folder 5)
      - Undated (Folder 5A)
    - Letters to Mr. & Mrs. C. S. Preble
      - 1911-12 (Folder 6)
      - 1914-16 (Folder 7)
      - 1917-19 (Folder 8)
  - Stines, Norman C., Senior (Box 4.)
    - 1935, 1940-41, 1953 (Folder 1)
    - Letters from Norman C. Stines, Jr.
      - 1933, 1935 (Folder 2)
      - 1936-1942 (Folder 3)
      - 1946--48, 1950-51, 1953-54 (Folder 4)
  - Teresa, 1946 (Folder 5)
  - Travers, Howard K. (Folder 6)
- Speeches and Writings, 1941, 1963
  - This is La Paz, January 1941., Radio broadcast transcript. (Box 4., Folder 7)
  - Trip from Caracas West, November 1964., Typescript. (Folder 8)
- Subject File
  - Bolivia (Box 4., Folder 9)
  - Miscellany (Folder 10)
- Photographs (Box 81097 - 10.A-V)
  - 13 prints depicting N.C. Stines Jr. and Senior and other individuals. (Folder A)
  - 62 prints depicting scenes and individuals in Russia., 1917 (Folder B)
  - 49 prints depicting scenes and individuals in Finland and Russia., 1917-18 (Folder C)
  - 72 prints depicting scenes and individuals in Finland., 1918 (Box D)
  - 16 prints depicting scenes and individuals in Serbia., 1920 (Box E)
  - 15 prints depicting scenes and individuals in Guatemala., 1940s (Box F)
  - 150 prints depicting scenes and individuals in Bolivia. (Folder G-J)
  - 52 prints depicting scenes and individuals in La Paz, Bolivia. (Folder K-L)
  - 33 prints depicting scenes and individuals in Potosi, Bolivia. (Box M)
  - 28 prints depicting scenes and individuals in Cochabamba, Bolivia. (Folder N)